Thank you very much, everybody, well, very, very much.
Vice President Vance, Speaker Johnson, Senator Thune.
Chief Justice Roberts, justices of the United States Supreme Court, President Clinton, President
Bush, President Obama, President Biden, Vice President Harris, and my fellow citizens.
The Golden Age of America begins right now.
From this day forward, our country will flourish and be respected again all over the world.
We will be the envy of every nation, and we will not allow ourselves to be taken advantage
of any longer.
During every single day of the Trump administration, I will very simply put America first.
Our sovereignty will be reclaimed, our safety will be restored, the scales of justice will
be rebalanced, the vicious, violent, and unfair weaponization of the Justice Department
and our government will end.
In our top priority, we need to create a nation that is proud, prosperous, and free.
America will soon be greater, stronger, and far more exceptional than ever before.
I return to the presidency confident.
it, an optimistic that we are at the start of a thrilling new era of national success.
A tide of change in sweeping trees, sunlight is pouring over the entire world, and America
has the chance to seize this opportunity like never before.
But first, we must be honest about the challenges we face.
While they are plentiful, they will be annihilated by this great momentum that the world is now
witnessing in the United States of America.
America.
As we gather today, our government confronts a crisis of trust.
For many years, a radical and corrupt establishment has
extracted power and wealth from our citizens.
The pillars of our society lay broken and seemingly
incomplete disrepair.
We now have a government that cannot manage even a simple
crisis at home, while at the same time stumbling into a
continuing catalog of catastrophic events abroad.
It fails to protect our magnificent law-abiding American citizens,
but provide sanctuary and protection for dangerous criminals,
many from prisons and mental institutions,
that have illegally entered our country from all over the world.
We have a government that has given unlimited funding to the defense of foreign borders,
but refuses to defend American borders or, more importantly,
its own people. Our country can no longer-
to deliver basic services in times of emergency,
as recently shown by the wonderful people
of North Carolina, been treated so badly.
And other states who are still suffering
from a hurricane that took place many months ago,
or more recently, Los Angeles,
where we are watching fires still tragically burn.
From weeks ago, without even a token.
of defense. They're raging through the houses and communities, even affecting some of the
wealthiest and most powerful individuals in our country, some of whom are sitting here
right now. They don't have a home any longer. That's interesting. But we can't let this happen.
Everyone is unable to do anything about it that's going to change. We have a public health system
that does not deliver in times of disaster. Yet more money is spent.
on it than any country anywhere in the world.
And we have an education system that teaches our
children to be ashamed of themselves, in many
cases, to hate our country despite the love that
we try so desperately to provide to them.
All of this will change starting today, and it
will change very quickly.
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
My recent election is a mandate to completely and totally reverse a horrible betrayal and
all of these many betrayals that have taken place and to give the people back their faith,
their wealth, their democracy, and indeed their freedom.
This moment on America's deadline is over.
Our liberties and our nation's glorious destiny will no longer be denied, and we will immediately
restore the integrity, competency, and loyalty of America's government.
Over the past eight years, I have been tested and challenged more than any president in
our 250-year history, and I've learned a lot.
along the way.
The journey to reclaim our Republic has not been
an easy that I can tell you.
Those who wish to stop our cause have tried to take
my freedom and, indeed, to take my life.
Just a few months ago in a beautiful Pennsylvania field
and a Sassan's bullet ripped through my ear.
But I felt then and believe even more so now
that my life was saved.
for a reason.
I was saved by God to make America great again.
Thank you very much.
That is why each day, under our administration of American patriots, we will be able to meet
every crisis with dignity and power and strength.
We will move with purpose and speed to bring back hope, prosperity, safety, and peace for
citizens of every race, religion, color, and creation.
for American citizens January 20th, 2025 is Liberation Day.
It is much that our recent presidential election will be remembered as the greatest
and most consequential election in the history of our country.
As our victory showed, the entire nation is wrapped.
rapidly unifying behind our agenda with dramatic
increases in support from virtually every element
of our society, young and old men and women,
African Americans, Hispanic Americans, Asian Americans,
urban, suburban, rural.
And very importantly, we had a powerful win in all
seven swing states.
And the popular vote, we won by millions of people.
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
To the black and Hispanic communities, I want to thank you for the tremendous
outporn of love and trust that you have shown me with your vote. We set records
and I will not forget it. I've heard your voices and the campaign and I look
forward to working with you in the years to come. Today is Martin Luther King Day
and his honor, this is a great honor, but in his honor we will strive.
Together to make his dream a reality. We will make his dream come true
National unity is now returning to
America. And confidence and pride is soaring like never before. In everything we do, my
administration will be inspired by a strong pursuit of excellence and unrelenting success.
We will not forget our country. We will not forget our Constitution. And we will not
forget our God. Can't do that.
Today, I will sign a series of historic executive orders.
With these actions, we will begin the complete restoration of America and the revolution
of common sense.
So all about common sense.
I will declare a national emergency at our southern border.
All illegal entry will immediately be halted, and we will begin the process.
All illegal entry will be halted, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process, and we will begin the process
of returning millions and millions of criminal
aliens back to the places from which they came.
We will reinstate my remain in Mexico policy.
I will end the practice of catch and release.
And I will send troops to the southern border
to repel the disastrous.
invasion of our country.
Under the orders I signed today, we will also be
designating the cartels as foreign terrorist organizations.
And by invoking the Alien Enemies Act of 1798, I will direct our government to use the full
and immense power of federal and state law enforcement to eliminate the presence of all
foreign gangs and criminal networks, bringing devastating crime to U.S. soil, including
our cities and inner cities.
As Commander-in-Chief, I have no higher responsibility than to defend our country
from threats and invasions, and that is exactly what I am going to do.
We will do it at a level that nobody has ever seen before.
Next I will direct all members of my Cabinet to marshal the vast powers at their disposal
to do what was record inflation and rapidly bring down costs.
prices. The inflation crisis was caused by massive
overspending and escalating energy prices. And that is why
today I will also declare a national energy emergency.
We will drill baby drill.
America will be a manufacturing nation once again, and we have something that no other
manufacturing nation will ever have, the largest amount of oil and gas of any country on earth,
and we are going to use it.
We will bring prices down, fill our strategic reserves up again right to the top, and export
American energy all over the world.
We will be a rich nation again, and it is that liquid gold under our feet that will
help to do it.
With my actions today, we will end the Green New Deal, and we will revoke the election.
electric vehicle mandate, saving our auto industry and keeping my sacred pledge to our
great American auto workers.
In other words, you'll be able to buy the car of your choice.
We will build automobiles in America again at a rate that nobody could have.
have dreamt possible just a few years ago.
And thank you to the other workers of our nation
for your inspiring vote of confidence.
We did tremendously with it.
I will immediately begin the overhaul of our trade system
to protect American workers and families.
Instead of taxing our citizens to enrich other countries,
we will tariff and tax foreign countries.
to enrich our citizens.
For this purpose, we are establishing the external revenue
service to collect all tariffs, duties, and revenues that will be
massive amounts of money pouring into our treasury, coming from
foreign sources.
The American dream will soon be back and thriving like now.
ever before, to restore competence and effective
governance to our federal government.
My administration will establish the brand new
Department of Government Efficiency.
After years and years of illegal and unconstitutional
federal efforts to restrict
free expression.
I will also sign an executive order to immediately stop all government censorship and bring
back free speech to America.
Never again will the immense power of the state
be weaponized to persecute political opponents.
Something I know something about.
We will not allow that to happen.
It will not happen again.
Under my leadership, we will restore fair, equal, and impartial justice
under the constitutional rule of law.
And we are going to bring law and order back to our cities.
This week, I will also end the government policy of trying to socially engineer race
and gender into every aspect of public and private life.
We will forge a society that is colorblind and merit-based.
As of today, it will henceforth be the official policy of the United States government that
there are only two genders, male and female.
This week, I will reinstate any service members who can justly expelled from our military
for objecting to the COVID vaccine mandate with full back pain.
I will sign in order to stop our warriors from being subjected to radical political
and social experiments while on duty.
It's going to end immediately.
Our armed forces will be free to focus on their sole mission,
defeating America's enemies.
Applause
In 2017, we will again build the strongest military the world has ever seen.
We will measure our success not only by the battles we win, but also by the wars that
we end, and perhaps most importantly, the wars we never get into.
My proudest legacy will be that of a peacemaker and
unifier.
That's what I want to be, a peacemaker and a unifier.
I'm pleased to say that as of yet.
yesterday, one day before I assumed office, the hostages in the Middle East are coming
back home to their families.
Thank you.
America will reclaim its rightful place as the greatest,
most powerful, most respected nation on Earth,
inspiring the awe and admiration of the entire world.
A short time from now, we are going to be changing the
name of the Gulf of Mexico to the Gulf of America,
and we will restore the name of a great President,
William McKinley, to Mount McKinley,
where it should be.
at where it belongs. President McKinley made our country very rich through tariffs and
through talent. He was a natural businessman and gave Teddy Roosevelt the money for many
of the great things he did, including the Panama Canal, which has foolishly been given
to the country of Panama after the
The United States, I mean, think of this, spent more money
than ever spent on a project before and lost 38,000
lives in the building of the Panama Canal.
We have been treated very badly from this
foolish gift that should have never been made.
And Panama's promise to us has been broken.
The purpose of our deal and the spirit of our treaty
has been totally violated, American ships.
ships are being severe, overcharged, and not treated fairly in any way, shape, or form.
And that includes the United States Navy.
And above all, China is operating the Panama Canal, and we didn't give it a China.
We gave it to Panama, and we're taking it back.
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
Above all, my message to Americans today is that it is time for us to once again act
with courage, vigor, and the vitality of history's greatest civilization.
So as we liberate our nation, we will lead it to new heights of victory and success.
We will not be deterred.
Together we will end.
the chronic disease epidemic and keep our children safe, healthy, and disease-free.
The United States will once again consider itself a growing nation, one that increases
our wealth, expands our territory, builds our cities, raises our expectations, and carries
our flag into new and beautiful horizons.
And we will pursue our manifest destiny into the stars, launching American astronauts
to plant the stars in the stars and the stars in the stars and the stars in the stars.
and stripes on the planet Mars.
Ambition is the lifeblood of a great nation and right now our nation is more ambitious.
than any other—there's no nation like our nation.
Americans are explorers, builders, innovators, entrepreneurs, and pioneers.
The spirit of the frontier is written into our hearts.
The call of the next great adventure, downs from within our souls.
Our American ancestors turned a small group of colonies on the edge of a vast continent
into a mighty repose—
public of the most extraordinary citizens on Earth.
No one comes close.
Americans pushed thousands of miles through a rugged land of untamed wilderness.
They crossed desert-scaled mountains, braved untold dangers, won the Wild West ended slavery,
rescued millions from tyranny, lifted billions from poverty, harnessed electricity, split
the atom, launched mankind into the heavens.
and put the universe of human knowledge
into the palm of the human hand.
If we work together, there is nothing we cannot do,
and no dream we cannot achieve.
Many people thought it was impossible for me
to stage such a historic political comeback.
But as you see today, here I am.
The American people have spoken.
Thank you.
Cheers and applause.
I stand before you now as proof that you should never believe that something is impossible
to do. In America, the impossible is what we do best.
From New York to Los Angeles, from Philadelphia to Phoenix, from Chicago to Miami, from Houston,
to right here in Washington, D.C., our country was forged and built by the generations of
patriots who gave everything they had for our rights and for our freedom.
They were farmers and soldiers, cowboys and factory workers, steel workers and coal miners,
police officers and pioneers.
who pushed onward, marched forward, and let no obstacle
to their spirit or their pride.
Together, they laid down the railroads,
raised up the skyscrapers, built great highways,
won two world wars, defeated fascism and communism,
and triumphed over every single challenge that they faced.
After all, we have been through together.
We stand on the verge of the four greatest years.
years in American history.
With your help, we will restore our American promise,
and we will rebuild the nation that we've been.
We love it so much.
We are one people, one family, and one glorious nation
under God.
So, to every parent who dreams for their child,
and every child who dreams for their future,
I am with you, I will fight for you,
and I will win for you.
We are going to win like never before.
Thank you.
In recent years, our nation has suffered greatly, but we are going to bring it back
and make it great again, greater than ever before.
We will be
nation like no other full of compassion courage and exceptionalism, our power will stop all wars
and bring a new spirit of unity to a world that has been angry, violent, and totally unpredictable.
America will be rescinded again and admired again, including by people of religion, faith,
and goodwill. We will be prosperous. We will be proud. We will be strong and we will win like
never before.
Or we will not be conquered.
We will not be intimidated.
We will not be broken.
And we will not fail.
From this day on, the United States of America will be a free, sovereign and independent nation.
We will stand bravely.
We will live proudly.
We will boldly and nothing will stand in our way because we are Americans.
The future is ours and our golden age has just begun.
Thank you, God bless America.
Thank you all.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.